Guide to the Elisha Lord Cleaveland Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Elisha Lord Cleaveland papers
1834-1866
MS 139
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
11
(32 boxes)
The papers deal chiefly with his ministry in the Third Congregational Church of New Haven and include diaries, account books, clippings, lecture notes, and sermons. The 1,300 sermons make up three-fourths of the papers. His diaries (1850-1864) are largely a record of his ministerial duties, but also contain an account of his brother's death (December 1863) and of his visits to a criminal condemned to be executed (July 1846). The lecture notes were apparently intended for use at the Andover Theological Seminary.
Cleaveland, Elisha Lord, 1806-1866
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Ruth Cleaveland Monroe, 1959.
Scope and Contents
These papers of Elisha Lord Cleaveland deal largely with his ministry in the Third Congregational Church of New Haven, Connecticut, from 1833 until his death in 1866. Three quarters of the papers consist of sermons by Cleaveland in a series numbered up to 1,402; approximately 1,300 are preserved here. Other writings by Cleaveland include notes on various subjects, and a number of lectures, some bound in notebooks and apparently intended for use at Andover Theological Seminary.
Three diaries, a record of ministerial duties, and a journal provide insight into Cleaveland's ministry. All five volumes detail church activities, texts of sermons preached and heard, visits to parishioners, and so forth, as well as occasional personal matters such as his reading, his health, and visits to neighboring towns. Some family events are recorded, including the prolonged illness and death of his brother, John, in December 1863 (folder 4). While routine church duties form the bulk of the contents of these volumes, there are some unusual items. The record of ministerial duties provides an account of Cleaveland's visits to a condemned criminal and of his feelings while officiating at the execution (folder 3a, Jul 1846), and an account of a daughter's mystical experience (Feb 1848).
Other miscellaneous items contained here are: an account book of the Third Congregational Society of New Haven; a personal account book; clippings about the Third Society and copies of other newspaper articles; and a certificate recording Trumbull Cleaveland being made a church member.
Arrangement
Arranged in two parts: Diaries, accounts, and related materials; Sermons.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Elisha Lord Cleaveland was born in 1806 and died in New Haven, Connecticut on February 16, 1866. He was a clergyman and author. He graduated from Bowdoin college in 1829, Andover Seminary in 1832, and attended Yale Theological Seminary.
Source: The Geneology of the Cleveland and Cleaveland Families, by Edmund Janes Cleveland, 1899.
For a chart outlining the genealogical relations of the Cleaveland family, please consult the Genealogical Chart.
Congregational churches -- Connecticut; Death; Executions and executioners; Theology -- Study and teaching; New Haven (Conn.) -- Religion; Sermons; Diaries; Clergy; Cleaveland, Elisha Lord, 1806-1866; Andover Theological Seminary; Third Congregational Church (New Haven, Conn.); Third Congregational Society (New Haven, Conn.)
- Inventory, 1834-1866; 11; (32 boxes)
  - Diaries, accounts, and related materials
    - Diary
      - 1850-1855 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - 1855-1860 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - 1864 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Record of ministerial duties, 1845-1850 (Box 1, Folder 3a)
    - Journal [of ministerial duties], 1860-1866 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Account book kept with the Third Society of New Haven, 1842- 1866 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Account book, 1856-1866 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Clippings concerning the Third Congregational Society of New Haven, Undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Certificate of Trumbull Cleaveland's having been made a church member, 1866 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - 27 sermons [by ELC's uncle, John Cleaveland, 1749/50-1815?], 1807-1810
      Existence and Location of Originals
      Transferred to John Cleaveland Papers (MS 882), 1983 Jan 7.
    - Copies of newspaper articles, 1774-1776, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Notes, Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Unidentified address "In Behalf of Seamen", Undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Unidentified notebook for lecture Andover Theological Seminary, Professor [Moses?] Stuart, [Circa 1810-1848] (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Unidentified notebooks for lectures [Andover Theological Seminary?], [Circa 1810-1848] (Box 3, Folder 14-17)
    - Lectures by ELC, 1839-1840, 1851 (Box 4)
  - Sermons (Box 5)
    - Catalog of Sermons, vol. I, nos. 1-517, 1832-1844 (Box 5)
    - Catalog of Sermons, vol. II, nos. 518-899, 1844-1853 (Box 5)
    - Nos. 59-78 (Box 5)
    - Nos. 79-80, 82-100 (Box 6)
    - Nos. 107-112, 118, 120-133 (Box 7)
    - Nos. 134-138, 140-155 (Box 8)
    - Nos. 156-179 (Box 9)
    - Nos. 180-186, 188, 190, 223-231, 233-237 (Box 10)
    - Nos. 238, 240-244, 267-286 (Box 11)
    - Nos. 287-319 (Box 12)
    - Nos. 320-327, 329-335, 337, 339-370, 373-374, 378-381, 383-386 (Box 13)
    - Nos. 391-392, 398, 403, 405-406, 409-410, 413-416, 419, 425, 428, 432-433, 435, 437, 442-444, 446-448, 452-453, 456, 481-484, 487-489, 491-492, 496-497, 501-511, 513-515, 576-589 (Box 14)
    - Nos. 591-592, 595, 597, 599-600, 602-603, 606, 610-623, 625, 627-632, 636-676 (Box 15)
    - Nos. 677-688, 690-710, 712-719, 721-727 (Box 16)
    - Nos. 729-762 (Box 17)
    - Nos. 763-789, 792-793, 795-796 (Box 18)
    - Nos. 799-804, 806-810, 812-813, 815, 829-847 (Box 19)
    - Nos. 849-855, 857-880 (Box 20)
    - Nos. 881-886, 888-922 (Box 21)
    - Nos. 923-925, 927-957 (Box 22)
    - Nos. 958-975, 977-990 (Box 23)
    - Nos. 991-999, 1034, 1036-1059 (Box 24)
    - Nos. 1061, 1063-1065, 1067-1071, 1073-1100 (Box 25)
    - Nos. 1101-1120, 1122-1131, 1133-1135 (Box 26)
    - Nos. 1136-1150, 1152-1166 (Box 27)
    - Nos. 1167, 1169-1187, 1189-1197, 1199-1200, 1233-1239 (Box 28)
    - Nos. 1240-1256, 1259-1265, 1267-1275 (Box 29)
    - Nos. 1276-1293, 1295-1305 (Box 30)
    - Nos. 1306-1330, 1361-1368 (Box 31)
    - Nos. 1369-1370, 1372, 1374, 1376-1402 (Box 32)